welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
so welcome to stoah let's do some
check-ins I'm feeling sort of a
lightness little sad yeah
vulnerable so the stole is a place for
us to cohere and dialogue but what
matters most at the knife's edge of this
moment and I'm Peter Limburger at the
Stewart and today we are lucky to have
my favorite trickster Alexander bard and
before we begin I wanted to like
apologize to bard let's just say that I
wasn't the best friend to him and he
knows why so I just want to say I'm
sorry and that being said I removed a
raven all right
hi everyone I'm Raven I'm gonna be
hosting the Q&A today so let's describe
what we're gonna be doing so we're gonna
have bard talking for about 20 to 25
minutes and then we'll move into cue a
warm woman up with some questions from
Peter and and I and then we'll open up
to Q&A from the audience
you can put your questions in the chat
and I will call your name and you can
ask your question to bard and with that
to the trickster himself Alexander
I meet yourself sir there we go
it's wonderful to be here and thank you
so much Peter and Raven for having me
and and Peter whatever that concerned
your your apology is completely accepted
in it and hey I'm not thesis guy in the
world to deal with and you you grow
every day in everything you do so a
total deep breed probably love in your
direction right away and don't worry
about a thing and Raven so nice to have
you here by the way this is queen raven
sam just her slave so she will decide
whatever she wants this evening and and
yeah i'll leave everything the control
button is hers
so I'll just I'll just take a few
minutes to do to do the presentation and
then we can move to the questions and
answers that I very much look forward to
so when I discussed this this thing
about stoah and how it could possibly
participate with Peter last week we can
take the conclusion that it could be
good time to sort of touch base and
we're react because obviously a major
event just going on in the world and and
the way you know that a major event is
going on to the world it's the fact that
you have to tell exactly which date
you're talking this is this happens to
be April 24 2020 and and because things
are changing it's just a rapid pace it's
impossible to talk about what's going on
in the world right now without actually
referring to the date and I can't think
of anything I can't do anything more
evident when it comes to defining an
event than this now the weird thing is
this that this all all sort of relates
to a pandemic that we call the corona
pandemic I prefer to call it the grand
corona right now because it's way more
than a pandemic pandemics aren't rare we
usually have say about seven or eight
major global pandemics like this every
century or so it's just that we've been
lucky you haven't had a major pandemic
like this that we know at least and well
the last time was the Hong Kong flu
which is called the late 1960s before
the Asian flu in the late 1950s it's
possible the corona is gonna get even
worse than those
but they were pretty bad they should
flew in 1957-58 killed about five
million people in the world and we had
about half the population that we do now
or even less so it would take the corona
to kill ten billion million people to
get there it's it's it's not unlikely
that would happen it's very likely
actually the Cronus killed far more
people those statistics allows right now
we have a you know major bad situations
in many parts of the world right now
even in countries they've declared only
40 or 50 people dead we have you know
rebellion already happening so this is a
bad situation but the pandemic itself is
not that unique what is unique is that
this is the first major pandemic in the
Internet age and and that makes it
different I also say that we probably
probably by early merge which is more
than a month ago
the pandemic was no longer the major
problem to the world but actually the
hysteria surrounding the pandemic has
become much more of a problem since
death and I would say this not
lightheartedly
without making myself much of a mess or
mixed him hating those things I've
suffered a really bad boot of copy 19
myself and I was really sick for a
couple of weeks and I also got it back
again
which warned me that this is not
something you easily get over it's not a
regular flu at all and and I've lost a
couple of friends already and I know a
lot of men my age I'm in my mid-50s that
have gone really sick from from this
virus so it's it's not something you
play around with lightly at all and I'm
glad my father died a respectful death
last year 87 years old because he's one
of those men out there who wouldn't
stand a chance if he'd been hit by the
copy 19 I would know cuz I did myself
but having said that even more so having
said that with the credibility to come
so it actually haven't suffered from the
virus and had a bad boot of it I would
say that we are now way past the point
where the pandemic is the problem rather
it's the stereo now that's of course
also interesting not only in a cynical
way there's also creative opportunity
coming out of creative destruction that
means that if you learn from history one
of our previous pandemics we know that
even the worst pandemics ever even like
the plague in the 14th century came with
certain benefits
I would even say that the plague in the
6th century was in worse because it
killed my favorite religion
zoroastrianism and replaced of a
religion that I detest called Islam so
personally I would say that the the
plague in the 6th century was the really
bad one the peg in the 14th century was
better in many ways it actually created
the opportunity for the renaissance and
eventually of course the Enlightenment
and the Reformation in Europe so we
don't know where this is gonna end up
it's probably not gonna be on that type
of scale at all
but I would definitely say this is a
major event seen over the last 3040
years it's a global event and as I said
this is the first major pandemic of the
Internet age so in what ways this
different well we're all connected we
have a population of about 8 billion
people on this planet and after the
majority of people on the planet today
are connected to the Internet through
the smartphones and laptops and other
gadgets and increasingly also more and
more intelligent machines around us are
getting connected
some people even force their pets to go
online these days apparently we'll call
me nineteen tests but there's far more
people connected than ever before in
history and we are directly connected
one another now I've written books about
this I worked on this for the past 30
years it's actually the reason why I
wanted to become a philosopher in the
first place because I thought the
Internet is such a dramatic revolution
that it has to be covered by philosophy
it is it is a phenomenon that even my
favorite philosophers like Hegel and
Nietzsche could never even have thought
about they could have comprehended you
know only 100 150 years ago that this
phenomena would occur in history so the
Internet itself is one of the biggest
events ever this means that the old
power structure that were built
basically on the printing press and the
fact that we made people around the
world who gained the capacity to read
write and count and following later you
know 2 300 years after printing was a
printing press was invented it became
affordable for people around the world
to read write and count and they did on
a massive scale and this of course
created the paradigm that was basically
dominated by what we called the West
which is Europe and eventually the three
other
content is the Europeans colonized and
plundered to take over the world that's
the world we lived in then starting in
the 1980s named Kenneth came along and
we could have ready then start thinking
of the world differently because we'd
actually what we tend to forget about
we'd actually gone through another
technological revolution just before the
internet arrived that made it easier for
us to comprehend it and that was flying
you know we had a mythology of Icarus an
occurrence trying to reach the Sun and
getting killed in the process because it
was hubris tick to think that you could
ever fly like a bird and although we
tried in so many ways at the end of the
19th century managed to figure out how
we could build machines with which we
could take the human body up into the
sky so we started flying
we started flying more and more and we
started using you know flights or planes
during warfare and discovered there were
also great weapons and eventually we put
a bomb inside one of those flights and
put that flight over a little town
called Hiroshima in Japan in on August
6th 1945 and dropped a bomb on it and
and I still as of a loss of her think
that that major event again an event
that changes history forever
that major event is still something
we're dealing with we have hardly even
started to understand what it means that
we as human beings have created a
technology which could wipe us out and
hardly any time at all
of course I led to the Cold War it also
led to the breakdown of phallic
Authority of the idea that men out there
who are engineers or whatever they are
could build a better world for tomorrow
it led us into a real awakening that was
both needed and understandable and we
call post-modernism today and it was the
question all could there be any phallic
Authority or could we replace it with
something else
that's the kind of work philosophers
like I work with like what kind of
narrative actually makes sense to human
beings and how are we as human beings
connected with one another so
this leads the song to the 1980s
postmodern already become the dominant
mode at least in the West post-colonial
studies were taken on meaning that the
rest of the world was starting to
respond to the fact the West had
conquered three other continents
plundered them and you know Hitler
wasn't the bad guy here he basically
just mimicked what Europeans did in
North America about fifty years before
him so this had already happened on a
massive scale and we were starting to
realize that we were increasingly live
in a globalized world they're just
saying apology apologies to other
cultures you plundered and braved could
be a fairly good idea at least as a
start because we're living increasing a
globalized world but then the internet
came along and connected all of us
directly you could already see in the
late 1980s that all the computers that
we were already using and now become
personal computers affordable personal
computers from the vast majority of
people we're now connected directly one
another so from the late 1980s you could
figure out that okay so all the
computers are directly connecting one
another meaning they're turning into one
huge computer and there's one huge
computers now connecting everybody on
the planet and eventually you could
figure out that my hard drive is not
going to be the only place where date
that's being stored from all this
communication that goes on where are we
gonna build you data centers eventually
and these data centers gonna be
incredibly powerful and probably gonna
call them tech giants in say 20 or 30
years time that's exactly the sort of
society we arrived at and philosophers
figured that out worthy 30 years ago and
we're now seeing this pattern and I want
to tie the pattern into the idea that at
the same time as we created the atomic
bomb and he scared the shit out of us we
all sent the satellites up into the sky
I would say if we're really honest about
it and the way we have to look at
history and hint sight is that after the
Tomic bomb were made another big mistake
who went to the moon we don't like to
think of it that way it's one of those
things that I like to question as a
trickster but when we went to the moon
in the late 1960s and put a few guys on
the moon who jumped around
the moon put a flag there turned out to
be the American flag because the
Russians are smart enough not to waste
hundreds of billions of dollars and
getting there but the Americans did and
if we look back at it now and the moon
banding oh we didn't go back didn't we
no we left a flag there yeah on what a
cold rock full of radiation there wasn't
any point along there and if you're
gonna look at the whole sort of
retelling of the narrative of the past
400 years and started cliched or was
great with for example European conquest
of half the planet and was bad with it
we also have to look at the difference
between the last territorial conquest
successful conquests in a cynical way
that successful conquest that both
occurred in the late 1950s and
ironically was the two countries do we
called the superpowers today I would say
that the probably the two worst
countries in the world right now because
one of them created the corona virus and
the other one created the corona Osteria
they called China the United States and
at the end of the 1950s China conquered
Tibet and if you're you know a Buddhist
and you you'd like to think that the
Tibetan people would be better off
without the Chinese we're not sure about
that but the China conquered Tibet but
at the same time the United States
conquered Hawaii after Americans had
killed probably about 90% of the
original Aboriginal population Hawaii
decimated into nothing and then a bunch
of American senior citizens they wants
to try to avoid Corona at the moment
decided to settle there and make it the
most expensive and beautiful place on
the planet
let's call Hawaii but Hawaii was
conquered literally by the United States
included us a state in the United States
same Thomas Tibet was included as a
state in China I found that very
interesting because that was also the
end of territorial expansion there's no
opportunity for any more territorial
expansion after the conquest of Tibet in
Hawaii and the funny thing is that ten
years later we sent a man to the moon
and we declared that a victory what
we're not seeing is that putting people
on the moon and wasting hundreds of
billions of dollars in doing it we
delayed the movement of hundreds of
millions of Indians and Chinese into the
middle class
happen only 3040 years later with no
help from merica yurop because he spent
so much money the 1960s of putting a guy
on the moon and declaring that a victory
which is nothing but symbolic and no
value at all I think that's a very
important lesson to learn so that we can
go back to the late 1950s and then ask
ourselves so what was the point going
into outer space in the first place well
there was something fantastic about it
it's called satellites and if we think
of something that ties airplanes whether
they're full of bombs or people that we
travel with today because we're the
flights at least the flights we had
before the corona we could travel for
one point on the planet to the opposite
part of the planet in less than 24 hours
that is amazing and we're digital we can
literally travel in 0.1 second so we can
play computer games between Finland and
New Zealand isn't that wonderful right
so we have arrived in a world which I
would call aarrow digital or spatial
digital in the sense that we now have
satellites that cover the entire planet
and these are listed two things for us
they both look at us we was called
something called the father case this is
like the you know the idea is that the
goddess is earth and then the God is up
in the sky and the God looks down and I
was like these are fatherly sonic gays
and looks down on us on the planet and
of course if you just use Google Maps
you figure out that's exactly what's
happening right now because we're
increasingly getting satellites to get
more and more powerful and to look over
the entire planet and they can look down
on anything that happens on the planet
the zoom in on it and where that comes
data you know we can now educate
ourselves by looking at anywhere in the
planet and then zoom in on a place on
the planet and learn about the people
who live there learn the language learn
the culture learn everything about them
and interact with which is amazing the
power of this is just fantastic
now it should also scare the shit out of
us because of two different versions of
understanding this idea of a satellite
world and one of them is that you
we got a lot of problems as humanity we
need to lock up the bombs somewhere
after this pandemic we also discovered
that what could be worse than a pandemic
would be biological weapons so we need
to figure out how we look those certain
particulars on them we're gonna have
chemical weapons more than ever
okay we need to lock up the weapons okay
we also plan it the more or less
destroyed starting exactly with the
conquest of the planet and of all these
different territories and you know this
massive expansion territorial that we
did and we both mines everywhere and we
started plundering it and then we
started using oil and gas and coal to
burn this whole thing to get cheaper
tricity and we were almost at the point
when we realized okay this is gonna kill
us if you don't stop this as well this
will also increase the demand for a
different world order the problem is
that the new world order that's needed
and the can be made possible now we
could get data from anywhere on the
planet and boom that data into the
satellites and Silas turn reflect back
on us and communicate with us in an
intelligent way and we start building
artificial intelligent to this to boost
it even further we will create a sincere
will create a world where we have
sensors absolutely everywhere in the
atmosphere in the waters of the seas on
our bodies and I would even say that
it's likely that the number of sensors
will increase in density the more people
you have around so this is of course
we'd be doing other things is although
Bell today but we increasingly seeing
that these sensors are gonna be
everywhere and we're gonna interact with
technologies we machines just about
everywhere we go so it's a whole new man
versus machine relationship that's
maturing here it's connected to the
satellites he's connected to information
data flows okay it doesn't take too long
for somebody to start fantasizing about
what if I'm the guy at the top of this
whole thing it turns out that the
probably most powerful person on the
planet who also happens to rule the
country where the coronavirus started is
called si and ping and he asked that
fantasy
without fantasies that has been tried
before she hasn't been a very good
fantasy it is a fantasy that starts
either as a Peter Pan syndrome or is a
Caligula syndrome that means that he's
even an 11 year old who was appointed to
be the Emperor way too early in his life
and before he was mature enough to take
on that role only was somebody was
probably pretty sane but grew up in an
environment that was so damn crazy that
he came across a totally paranoid
character once it was given power
because it couldn't trust anybody
imagine you can have all the power in
the world you're the king of the world
but you can't trust anybody
it's called Caligula syndrome it's the
opposite of Peter Pan syndrome but in
any case it's disastrous because you all
know that only a guy who grows up in a
healthy nice environment and and becomes
you know and learns that he has a girl
he can become a woman and it can become
a shark or she can become a boy a man
c'mon patriarchy eventually unless we go
through these archetypal x' sort of
steps in our lives that we can take on
parenting we can take on teaching we can
take on adventure maybe even be elderly
of a community because we're wiser and
older we've been around long time unless
all these processes work and we appoint
eleven year olds to around the world or
people who are mentally are 11 year olds
we get a problem the problem starts with
acknowledge that in Egypt about 1300
before Christ when Egypt goes into a
really brutal ruthless dictatorship and
it was only after canard and died and
his son took a comma took over that the
priests of Egypt decided to kill the son
to get the whole shit out of the way
that leads us all the way up to the
beautiful Silk Route the connected East
the West still the most magnificent
construction in human history but what
happened in the 20th century is that the
payback from Europe in terms of ideas
was that we reverse the Silk Route and
repeated ignite all over again as if we
haven't learned from all these horrible
dictators throughout history would have
Hitler be one of them Mussolini be one
of them would it stop in one of them and
eventually the Asians caught on and they
got Mao Zedong and eventually
we get to the end of the 1960's and a
young Cambodian student at Sorbonne in
Paris writes a PhD or so it goes home to
his country Cambodia and kills two
million people starting with the people
who wore glasses
that's the madness of Peter Pan syndrome
and the problem today with a society and
especially now where the corona pandemic
is creating Kron hysteria is he says
suddenly people are asking themselves
okay we have the climate hysteria before
this so we want sensors everywhere so we
can keep track of climate so we can know
what climate change is going on and
where damage is being done so we can
have proper arguments target that we
don't want anymore oil or gas or coal
because we need to save the planets of
humanity because they here and we need
machines to help us with that we're
technologists help us with that all of
that was out there but the problem is
now with the pandemic going into
hysterical face and with eight billion
people sitting with megaphones in their
hands and not feeling that they have any
parents around to protect them so they
become children of a lesser God or they
shout at the top of their lungs and say
save me from this Malay the first thing
you're gonna see is that a lot of people
are gonna say oh wait a second if you
can just track your smartphone and if
you know exactly where your body is we
can lock up all the people who are evil
people and then we can make them into
scapegoats and everybody else can be
free and we can save them from the virus
we hear these voices everywhere we just
don't hear them in China no the Chinese
are used to because they've heard it
from a dictatorship from the Communist
Party for the past 4050 years now we
hear this now in East Asia we heard this
time across Europe where it is now in
the United States we're increasing here
in countries like Brazil the Mexico
where democracy is poor Iran so we're
hearing now is this voice that oh we
could use technology to control the
things we don't like that opens up the
door for seeing paying not being a
Chinese phenomena anymore but being
actually a local phenomena that could
easily become a universal phenomena in
that case and what I would like to
discuss is how we can contain the virus
enough to then contain the hysteria to
have a proper discussion on how we can
move towards as in soccer see because I
believe in it and I believe it's
unavoidable and I believe it has
enormous benefits but if you can live in
a world where the satellites look down
on us and we have data but just about
everything we do in the world can that
still be a world where power is so
decentralized and we can guarantee
plurality you can guarantee tolerance we
can guarantee openness because I believe
all those values and what we learn from
the past four or five thousand years of
history is that any culture that can
maintain those things will not be eleven
years of hell and havoc there rather be
thousands of years of prosperity can we
create a truly pluralistic sense ah
cracy I think that's the ants and we owe
to tell the world and we can direct it a
rattling see in ping hopefully making
more sign but wouldn't need an
alternative to the current Confucian
European fantasy a dictator is on his
way back thank you Thank You Alexander
and we already have like amazing
questions in the chat we're gonna start
I'm gonna ask Peter if you would like to
share your question yeah that was
amazing thank you my friend I have a
question that feels related but it's not
might not seem directly related and it's
a genre Viki he came to stow a couple
weeks ago and he said that this is
bubbling up in him he said he wanted to
steal the culture and it sort of been
like a rallying cry at the stove I like
let's steal the culture and a cure of
the dawn is given they're going to make
like a little nice tune on that a clip
of John and so I'm curious of your
thought if the culture needs to be
stolen how to do it and yeah I'll leave
at that I know I don't think the culture
native you stole I think the culture is
emerging if anything is emerging we're
partners John Ferraris favorite terms
actually make sense
it isn't this I give you an example of
what I did when I got the coffee 90 and
it got really sick okay
before that I knew the Asteria would be
incredibly problematic I'm an economist
by training and this is going definitely
to be the worst economic crisis the
world has seen since 1929 and we all
know historically that if we arrive at
an unemployment rate over 25 percent we
get rebellion it's already happening now
in Europe we got bad scenes happening in
the suburbs of Paris the lockdown is not
working at all so a softer approach
would probably be better to begin with
but I also knew when I got the coffee 19
I came home and I really asked him a
couple of friends had been sick like a
week or two before me
and I just connected with them and they
said you know what there are thousands
of men of our age out there who are
experiencing exactly the same symptoms
we just realized we're not going to die
when we're gonna have a really bad boot
of the disease and want to make sure our
fathers are not getting close to it
great and suddenly it was like I moved
into a world with thousands of men we're
doing parallel studies of a brand new
disease for a brand new virus now then I
suddenly saw yeah this is the beauty of
the Internet this is amazing that is
culture to me that is the new culture
this is digital culture it's best
it's in people directly find each other
and they can also use algorithms to find
people around the world who they can
communicate with and they can then
instantly create perfectly
scientifically viable studies oh they're
all nice and and of course I've got tons
of tips from there that I can now use
and my improvement is gotten a lot
better and of course I felt safe and
warm and protect that loved because I
was thrown into this tribal community
the subculture of men between 50 and 60
who realize that we're gonna have a bad
boo to this disease this is how we
survive it and support each other so the
cultures already emerging out there
because people are trained to think
tribally I'm totally against
individualism and openness collectivism
work I think human beings are deeply
tribal and that's why I love your work
Peter on the medic triage because it's a
great description of human beings are
not discovering about themselves when
they're reflecting their own humanity
into the digital
tribal comes back in a big way and out
of this comes culture already and
I wouldn't I wouldn't even dare to
speculate what kind of culture that is
but it spontaneously appearing it's it's
tribal
if beyond tribal is into tribal and it's
beautiful so it's already happening I'll
follow up question and this is out the
edge of my thinking's I'm really curious
if we can bounce off each other here my
sense is the next move is to try to make
mimetic tries to come embody tribes
I remember Sam Vaknin he's a narcissist
like the expert narcissism who is a
narcissist who got his nurses this is
why from his expertise traces like so
delicious there and then he said the
religion of tomorrow's gonna be the
religion of narcissism and of course
he's gonna say that and then I thought
about an icon maybe narcissism was like
an ecumenical religion and all these
like mimetic tribes people are
narcissistically attached to the ideas
they just want to spit it out so just
pause that for a moment and going back
to the kind of stealing the culture line
my sense is that culture and service of
ego is not what we need like we create
these cultural artifacts or bust up the
ego but culture should be kind of keep
ego in check or make it like a healthy
relationship with ego and so yeah I just
finish okay actually it's all old news
because it's called the Cartesian
individualism was invented by a French
artist called kinetic art in the 17th
century
it's then for example become the state
religion or North America especially of
the United States I should avoid
mentioning Canada and I always say that
when it come to America there's so many
things to love about America but one
thing is really tiresome is that
Americans do not understand that they
exclusively have religion called Cochise
individualism but Europeans have at
least started dealing with over the last
50 years and the rest of the world never
cared about so the thing is if you if
you go to the world of physics as a
great metaphor is that when something
comes at the end of its lifespan it
usually explodes and become like a big
supernova and in our book digital libido
you know so dickfist and i write
explicitly that we must understand that
hyper narcissism which is happening or
has happened may be corona finally
killed it has happened especially in the
2010s
at the end of a development starting in
the 70 century called katisa
individualism and of course when
everybody was told that you live in a
world with eight billion people who are
at constant competition one another and
in constant driver one another and now
we give you a tool where you can express
herself called the Internet it was
pretty obvious if we take about 30 years
of children's diseases and things like
that on the Internet where people
mistakenly thought the internet was the
way to sell themselves but I've always
told people that already in the early
1990s you started throwing away
newsletters some people only talked
about themselves all the time and if
usually men and there were over 40 years
old rain will probably agree with me
uuuugh tired of the men over 40 years
old and it's understandable that
everybody else go tournaments because
they thought well no foley I do need to
secretary wrote Madiba and I'm gonna
tell everybody what a good boy I am and
I'm gonna impress my mum right that's
what they always wanted you impress mom
by being this good boy who does amazing
things and always at the end of the
email you would have this is my new
record this is my new book you must buy
me well the end of that when even
teenage girls guitarra was called the
influencer and we ended up with the
influence and writing their own fan
clubs called echo chambers this was the
2010 and if anything that's now dead and
over and this is why I emphasized this
enormous difference between the youtuber
and an influencer because youtuber is
somebody takes on the role of being an
older brother an older sister to your
kid brothers and consistory and your
basic guide them through the world and
you problematize the world and you
discuss the world for hours and they
follow you because you give them
pictures and you give them sounds and
you tell them of something and I give
you perfect sample this I live with
Peter Towson who's like a savant and he
keeps sick of what's happening in China
for our team every morning and he
doesn't look at the news no he just
looks at these youtubers from China and
the usually Western guys her Merida
Chinese girls in the live in Shanghai
and they tell him everything about life
in China he's actually like the way a
really really good document or best
could do it maybe 30 years ago but that
no new support could ever recover well
of course
Peter knows more about China than any of
us guys who was sitting there watching
BBC or CNN
we know nothing compared damn that is
how you know learn so you just find the
people out there who credible who love
you like an older brother an older
sister would and you guide you with her
expertise through the landscapes you
know where to go and this is deeply
human this is important to be tribal in
the tribe you always look for a mentor
and we become their mentee and we become
younger versions of them and they have
the same archetype that we have the same
personality traits the same talents and
they just shows how to do things so we
can mimic creatively and learn this what
people are doing now so if this is the
2020s and if the corona was something we
need in between I would declare I've
seen the death of hyper narcissism it no
longer pays off we throw it in the spam
box we hate it but we love anybody
veidt's us to join the tribes anybody
comes to burn loving heart as I said
listen I'm a member of a community I
would love to invite you to remember our
community that's the future so yeah I
will I think we have a sense that we
should like talk offline or maybe come
into the podcast or something's I'd love
to chat with you more but what came
alive there was that you know my
assessment of culture war it's like we
can't win the culture war by playing
with the same weapons that are being
used right now and then what's something
alive
well maybe the culture was already over
I mean for God's sake America is going
to pick a precedent to November how
obvious can it be that the president
doesn't matter when you're chosen to
take two old Corona corpses and choose
between them just like I can't think of
anything more boring than look it's so
bad we're all thinking aren't we that
maybe they were both dead by November
you know it's yeah but maybe something
new that isn't the White House needs to
take over and hopefully it isn't Jeff
Bezos Amazon dictatorship that's what we
should look next thank you I'd love to
do it Peter let's do that together yeah
explore that to get tribalism yes yeah
I'd like to hear that okay so we have a
question from Samir where do you see the
phallic gaze pointing towards ie what is
the role of men in the transition ahead
and I would add to that as well what is
the role of women
okay so the cases are very important
here the magical case is foundational
the magical case of what meets you and
you're born and hopefully what you see
when you die so the magical gaze is it's
not your mother
it's your midwife it's usually the
grandmother it's an older woman who has
been leading the mother into her
motherhood so she gives birth to you so
when you actually when you come out and
first thing is like oh I want to die
where I want to get back in I don't want
to let and then somebody meets you with
a big smile on their face it's called
the magical gaze the magical gaze is the
gaze of unconditional love if you ever
experience that somebody just looked at
given the smart and I just loved you
beyond everything that's the magical
gaze so it's not gender-specific a man
can obviously give you a magical gaze we
call it the magical gaze because in the
order of things because we come out of
the female body and we also return to
the female body when we die the female
body is origin the female body is where
we come from and where we go to and in
this sense the male body and what we
call the phallus it's only like little
boys protest against how things actually
operate and that's all humanity could
ever hope for so what we do then with
the father case it is simply the other
gates that we need we grow up so far
this is just a name for leaving the
matrix and then leaving the mamela so we
leave first the body and then we're
unified with the female body again at
the Manoa and they would leave the
breast and we have to move on and they
would look at another world and it's
like Freud said it's wherever your
mother is looking but isn't you
hopefully is just looking at a man or if
she's a lesbian she's looking at a
girlfriend it doesn't matter but she's
looking somehow to something that you
cannot be yet and this creators the urge
inside the child that he wants to leave
the my mother wants to be independent he
wants to try its own way he wants to say
and now I want to do things my way okay
to one day become an adult
that means the phallic case looks at the
world first and then looks back at you
and it gives you an honest answer of
your potential it gives you the
straightforward answer you're looking
for it when you want to grow because you
can't give somebody smiling at you
unconditionally no matter what No
sometimes it just gets boring that all
the children get the same gold star on
every little painting they do and maybe
you want to be a little better than the
other guys at doing a painting and
you're going to rivalry and it turns out
you've got the talent to make it better
painting then you want to be the only
kid who gets the gold star and to get be
the only kid gets the gold star to
confirm that you have a specific talent
you need the founder case so in religion
the magical gaze is what we have down
here on earth usually we look to an
older woman and and tell me I've studied
tribes in the Amazons and in Greenland
places and the older woman is always the
person they're all terrified out she's
the matriarch wife you're all
responsible to her whether you're a man
or a woman but the phallic case were
looking for is usually an older man who
comes back from being out there in the
world and comes back in and he greets us
and he looks at what we're doing and
that's what we trust his judgment when
we go forward so we put the fella case
in the sky and that's what we're talking
about the satellites ask the replacement
of the Falak case so then so what risks
are there in terms of like the phallic
gaze from satellites you know being
taken over by authoritarianism or this
idea of like the Peter Pan syndrome like
how can that be perverted and what what
kind of cost will we incur especially
since we're also it seems like in this
matriarchal gaze like with how people
talk online and you know with social
justice like passive aggression that
seems to be like part of our discourse
and the megaphone is it on our digital
platforms seem to be stoking that so
what do you see and within that yeah it
actually relates to a peter discussed
before about the culture wars and if you
want to go beyond the culture wars i'm
trying to take more diplomatic styles in
between them and understand the better
it is the misunderstanding or pat
Sharkey and Matt Ricci and what they
actually mean tossed that is the problem
today and I always emphasize that I hate
the fact that patriarchy became a bad
word because Pat Turkey is just a word
for young men are looking for older men
for guidance but what I do then because
I love to use the word patriarchy to
provoke you
I always use the word metric in the same
sentences to emphasize that the matter
key in the Patrick you operate in
parallel and we're all included because
the master key is what we call the inner
circuit in any tribal construction
looked at and the Patrick is the outer
circuit but of course for the Patrick a
metric to be able to communicate in a me
flock animal you have a certain number
of people who become homosexuals and
transsexuals and wonderful beautiful
androgynous people so we call them
endogenous caste as anybody's been to
hair salon or being to a couple
therapists would know it takes gay
people to sort out the shit they had to
sexual people running to all the time so
we need them right we need about four or
five percent of them in there in general
population and that's exactly the
numbers we have and then we have another
four percent of the population that
actually are go between between tribes
they called shamanic caste people
they're the way or those of the strange
guys in the world we usually pull the
scapegoats from out of there and we
would pull somebody through the streets
and what hang and kill them is probably
shamanic person that we use the you know
any dirty work that needs to be down the
nobody was to touch like being you know
a brothel madam a sex worker or an
executioner any of those things are
shamanic traits shamanic personalities
we call them shaman oyd personalities
even in the world of psychology and I
find me credibly interesting to study
because they're also the only hope we
have at a paradigm shift like the
current one because if you're gonna have
some people who are gonna walk in
between tribes or in our case in between
nations or in between cultural spheres
you'll be able to talk to people then we
discover that when we put shaman old
people in a psychological laboratory
they don't understand things like skin
color they understand what other people
are concerned about people looking
different because there's a use to
they're born into a world where their
mind is just completely geared towards I
don't care about generally how her skin
call you have an account with each yeah
I'm beyond and weirdly in between those
things and these are the people we would
always find running around in the forest
taking the ultimate risks dying young
all those things that we attribute to
rock stars and the lesser gods are these
shamanic traits and we need them because
the only people we only have on our
block change their artificial
intelligence helping people to
communicate across cultural lines the
only people who naturally walk across
culture lines and are not affected by
them are shamanic cast people so we need
an audience and we need to amount of
people more than ever and I think by
stating that clearly we can go back to
defining what does it mean to be a
regular heterosexual man or regular
heterosexual woman and why are 95% of
all people like that and why isn't that
beautiful and powerful and then we can
overcome the culture war but I think
it's impossible unless we see the bigger
tribal human picture I really want to
keep digging into this but I'm going to
continue to ask questions in the chat is
the concept of herd immunity will it
kill the Western individual and wake
them up to their individual reality what
do you think about that
oh the herd immunity individualism okay
that was that was a weird question but
fascinating uh herd immunity is to me a
medical term so if you study
epidemiology and I'm a philosopher if
your loss of an immunity complexity
theorist of your complexity theorist and
three things you love metrology say
small oh gee and epidemiology why
because they involve human beings their
relations to the earth and they
incredibly complex upon the data so
that's why you study epidemiology if
you're a complexity theorist and a herd
immunity means that on average about 70
to 80 percent of general population have
to have had a certain say a virus in
this case so then when the virus comes
back possibly be needin even worse for
him the immunity is so strong that it
doesn't stick so you get very few people
if any people who get sick so you don't
get a second you don't get a second
epidemic in that case some countries are
obviously going towards that direction
Sweden is one of them for example where
I live
we're basically now accepting there with
50% of the population here in Stockholm
have already had the virus and exposed
to it we suffer higher death rate than
other countries do but the trick here is
that we don't expect vaccines to be
around until several years from now if
ever and because we can't count on the
back says to be around
it's better prepared to avoid the next
wave of the epidemic and allowed to pass
through the population and then the only
thing we need to sort out is that do we
have enough ventilators for people to
get sick so we say this man as he
possibly can but then we can avoid the
second and the third way when they come
now of course some countries will try to
start a gear other countries like New
Zealand it just said no we're just gonna
lock up the country and nobody's gonna
be able to enter and then we're just
gonna wait it out and have no idea where
we're gonna go next but at least we have
fewer deaths so that's what herd
immunity does I would say that I don't
see directly tying in to the question
individualism collectivism and tribalism
because I think the individualism
collectivism divide will be solved by a
dialectical route into tribalism which
also happens to be returned back into
deep history into what it means to be
human
any bad case I prefer to stay with the
Dunbar number and say that people can
accept another 157 grown-ups around them
it's called a clam I must accept the
clan with little storytelling and a few
narratives they can accept that we can
go into a tribe and be 1,500 or 2,000
people that you do not kill or envy too
much the problem that is anything larger
than that it's always a challenge for
Humanity and we all know that as soon as
you live together with more than the
tribe size we start to become criminals
and we start having disloyal just
towards one another and that's something
we struggle with for the past 10,000
years and we'll keep on struggling with
it for a long time hopefully now with
the help or more shaman's Amy would you
like to unmute yourself and ask your
question
hi sure so my question is very quick I
wanted to see if you could discern the
line between public safety and personal
responsibility and what you thought
about that thank you for a good question
yeah this comes down to trust so we all
know that cultures that people have
trusted each other for a long time
preferably we don't have to lock the
door when you leave the house I mean
that would be the ultimate evidence that
you trust your village neighbors right
we all know that the longer the chains
of trust are in the culture the more
people do take responsibility for one
another so it's easier and cheaper and
more efficient to go towards a society
at mineral cost for example you need a
pandemic if you're long chains of trust
now I'm not saying you must have that I
don't want to be more honest about it
there are highly efficient cultures
where the chains of trust are minimal I
would say that's probably the case and
some of these city-states around the
world where people are just moved in in
the last three generations and work
really hard and pay low taxes and you
have to take care of yourself and maybe
have a family or a congregation that you
trust the government is really usually
weak and small that's places like Dubai
and Hong Kong
I wouldn't expect people in Dubai and
Hong Kong to feel that they can trust
their neighbors the way you can in
Switzerland or Sweden
so I'm I'm no I don't want to be
moralistic about it all I'm saying is
that the longer and the stronger the
chains of trust are in a given society
the more the the opposition between
public safety and personal
responsibility becomes a non-issue
because it's interesting that I hear you
say this come from North America but I
don't hear any scam that even asked with
the same question because they would
automatically assume the public safety
personally don't to connect it it's just
a courtesy that you don't spit at your
neighbor and you babe you know behave
gracefully in society and you hopefully
avoid not getting too drunken and
sleeping with the wrong person at the
wrong time because we have academic at
the moment but but it is a cost-benefit
analysis you need to do and of course
I'm also a strong cosmopolitan 'us I'm a
strong proponent of cultures
intermingling with each other and
challenging people to take on strangers
I I love the big
Pyrus of history one of the trade routes
and I love the whorehouses in the bath
houses and everything dirty that went
with it right but I also know that the
price we pay we create larger
communities quickly is that the natural
change the trust that existed then
evaporate and then you need more
technology you need more machines we
need more help from intelligent machines
Jack should be able to trust one another
we need more block chains unless they
actually trust our neighbors naturally
so it's a trade-off thing great and then
we have a question here from Owen Owen
would you like to mute yourself and ask
your question to Bart hey Alexander
how's it going mate so I was thinking
about this fight against totalitarianism
and how I guess in the 20th century of
my liberty freedom has been perhaps the
ideal and the value that we hold up
against it I'm wondering if as we move
into a more sense or attic power
structure is there a new ideal that kind
of takes the place of freedom and
liberty that we can cling to or does
freedom and liberty still remain what we
go for thank you for a great question
the way I see it is that I tried to
avoid becoming moralistic so I don't go
into the sort of freedom versus
totalitarianism to say in itself rather
I want to have arguments where it pays
off to do the right thing for the right
reasons anyway and and it's better than
to look at the effects long-term effects
and here's the problem you know where
the coronavirus started spreading in
Hebei in China and the Chinese
authorities try to keep quiet about it
for about three to four months and they
basically punished anybody who told the
truth the funny thing was that I had all
these kids everywhere who just referred
back to the Chernobyl serious you know
that we knew or Chernobyl the year
before he's an old friend of mine John
rank did that and and Joanne's ambition
when he wrote you know was obviously not
to write about the Soviet Union but to
write about Communist China or basically
to write about the problem with any
totalitarian system because any
totalitarian system would have a little
boy Pharaoh at
top called the dictator he's an 11 year
old Peter Pan and he doesn't want to
hear anything that he doesn't like and
even if he understands listening to some
mentor that he should hear things he
doesn't like nobody dares to tell them
things they don't want to tell it that
means there's always he delay in any
system like that before the truth
reaches power and until truth reaches
power it cannot be executed on Sochi and
ping must have been shocked to find out
that everybody be kept quiet for about
four months about a pandemic that could
kill his power it could kill him so he
probably then went into reverse and
started looking like the you know the
tough guy is gonna lock up everybody and
lock them all in and of course China's
gone in that direction meaning now they
have a massive problem is that now when
the virus comes back into China
ninety-five percent of China were
covered by axion ping he was locked in
Roubaix but what are they gonna do now
1.2 1.3 billion Chinese people are
exposed to the virus anyway and he has
no solution to that it must he must shit
his pants every day with that problem
but this is also a great argument
against totalitarian so I would say the
best argument ever is that Stalin died
alone and if you go into the biography
of Stalin yours of Stalin he was
probably he was the king of the world
probably the most powerful person on the
planet when he died but he was so lonely
when he died that he was sick that none
of his doctors dared to go into the room
being afraid they'd be executed by if he
didn't like what they told him so they
they decided not to go into the room so
this guy died the lowliest death ever
Starlin died the longest death have he
died alone plagued by his decease not
being cured a treated basically because
the doctors decided let's just pretend
he's in there and we're not in there and
they we all save our asses Tameka get
out of here and that's exactly when you
when you kill when you killed the
dictator with the priests decide to kill
the tailor that's exactly what happens
that's that's a killing or Tutankhamun
Egypt and all the way up to Stalin's
death and I think that's a good story to
tell us that this system is deeply
dysfunctional and I loved it because
don't rank cleverly put Chernobyl out
there and the kids could understand that
what's going on in communist China today
well Chernobyl
and they did learn from Chernobyl that
actually when a disaster strikes then a
dictatorship is incredibly vulnerable
because it's the worst place for
disaster strike the other way of looking
at that is then to look at creativity so
we can look at a coat o penis and we
just saving the planet we can look
across the positives and which is
getting along with our neighbors any
dictator in the world could embrace that
that's for Singapore and Dubai are
dictatorships for practical purposes but
when when it comes to actually
creativity and if the economy is going
to be around and creative destruction
and then creative construction following
that we all know the China is really
good at mimicking things but any
innovation that takes place in China is
happening in Taiwan and Hong Kong it's
not happening in mainland China so the
really great argument here is that if
you're gonna have a system where we go
into what the old Iran is called the
flush of karate estate though ever
renewed creativity ok so imagine that is
the future then you know innit opium
future of fresh Arcadia
if that is ever going to happen it
cannot be in a dictatorship it must be
in some kind of pluralistic some sokrati
for that to happen all right
that's excellent great ok well we have
about five minutes here to wrap up
there's still this great question in the
chat ok I think maybe we'll try and
cover this one because it's it's about
the trickster archetype so Kevin do you
want to ask your question and then maybe
so you mentioned a few times the rule of
the like the shamanic sort of trickster
archetype wandering across cultural
lines how do you think that'll change or
has changed in a digital age when every
tribe is already connected and these
lines are really blurred and so how how
do you see that role changing or do you
have any people who you think embodies
archetype well in the digital sphere
great question I'm obsessed with shaman
oyd personalities but I should emphasize
that there's a serious or different
archetypes among the shaman or person
all these tricksters just one of them
and what's characteristic for the tricks
that East that he or
she just speak their mind and do not
care about the consequences
so the tricks there is always a person
who we must have in society but who we
can allow the right to not care about
the consequences of their behavior that
is different for example from say the
priest with another shaman or
personality semantics character the
priest is responsible for the outcome or
what it does actually he is the ultimate
strategist and if you put him inside the
court he's probably the ultimate
intrigue maker but but the priest is
very different from the tricks and
precisely in this domain and I'd love to
develop you further maybe we can do it
when we're off this little show here
tonight but but I'd love to develop
refer they were working a lot with these
characters and I'd like also sociology
and anthropology be able to pick up all
these ideas on the shamanic cast and
describe and identify different
shamonite personalities and of course
personally I'm involved in the sex
workers union in Europe and you know
it's a deep personal thing for me you
know and also to redefine drug addiction
because it's not really addiction it's
it's very natural for people to take
drugs sometimes especially if there's
shaman road personalities so uh maybe we
could even allow the shaman a person
ladders to have their own loss and do
their own things because there are a lot
of things that most of us cannot handle
couldn't do but we could even give a
license for some people to say you're
damned trickster or you're you're you're
allowed to take as many drugs as you
like and experiment why is it because
you are that personality type who should
we should afford as a society and for
the sake of tolerance and creativity to
go ahead and make these experiments that
would be amazing
yeah there's so much to talk about in
this area especially with like sex work
and how that's changing in the digital
era there's so much to talk about okay
so you really put a lot of really great
ideas in our heads and there's even more
great things coming up at the stoah so
we're going to talk about some of the
some of the events that are coming up
fard thank you so much for being here
thank you for having me raven and we all
know that everybody's watching because
of queen raven and i just went along
with the ride
because our so you're so beautiful in
terribly externally in every way
possible your good sister amazing having
you here too is amazing and I've been
following your work and it's so exciting
to actually have a conversation that
would you like to talk about a cure the
dawn Peter yes so our next event coming
up actually the next event is your event
Raven which I'll let you talk about but
the next event after that is 8:30 p.m.
Eastern Time
Akira that dawn is going to do some live
streaming on stoic needing ways so he
has like basically he didn't read marcus
aurelius is meditation to like you know
his music and so that's really dope he's
gonna have a live session here so you're
all invited
go to the website wptz.com which is a
very like controversial provoking game
and yeah everyone's welcome to come so
it's going to basically be you get mixed
up into breakout rooms for about eight
minutes with a stranger and you have a
provocative question that you both
answer together so that's going to be at
7 p.m. and then we also have some other
events coming up Amy would you like to
plug your your upcoming event sure I
don't know if I can plug it but
basically on the heat of the talking
about archetypes Louie will be kind of
exploring masculine feminine archetypes
and think they actually can be reformed
and recast in more contemporary terms
awesome a really important conversation
for us all to be having and then is
Tyson do you want to talk about your
event as well thank you yes freestyling
through a pandemic is the name of the
event and we will be exploring our
musicality and rhythm and poetry through
freestyle rap
and in my experience it has been one of
the most powerful ways for me to connect
with people and get to know people
experienced group flow is through music
and it's an especially interesting
experiment done through zoom on finding
and last time was really fun so we're
gonna build on that energy and momentum
and I look forward to flowing with you
all there that's tomorrow at 8:00
Eastern yeah I'm feeling nervous about
coming already
yeah but I'm excited all right and with
that we see the stoah as a gift for
everyone to be using at this time and if
you feel inspired to give a gift to the
Stila you can visit us at the stove ta
under the gift economy that we are we've
come to a close thank you everyone for
being here